

Curriculum Vitae for Robert Hagala

Personal information

Address: Hagelundveien 5 E-mail: rh@xal.no

0963 Oslo Phone: $+47\ 992\ 46\ 527$

Born: 12 June 1991 Nationality: Norwegian

Summary

I am finishing a PhD in astrophysics at the University of Oslo. My field of research is numerical N-body simulations in cosmology. Through my research I have developed expertise in numerical modeling, statistical and visual analysis of big data sets, signal processing, pattern recognition, high- and low-level programming, and code optimization. I have learned many complex concepts in science and technology, and demonstrated my ability to understand and combine many areas of knowledge. I consider myself an analytical, adaptive, and open-minded person with the ability to work highly individually and quickly adapt to unforseen circumstances.

Technical skills

Frameworks Numpy, Scipy, Matplotlib, MPI/OpenMP Languages Python, FORTRAN, C/C++, Java, PHP, R

Tools Git, Unix, Windows, Jupyter Notebook, OpenOffice, LATEX, Google

Education

2015 - 2019	Ph.D. in astrophysics (cosmology) at the University of Oslo, thesis tit-
	led "Astrophysical Simulations for Uncovering Signatures of Gravity".
	Supervisor: David F. Mota
2013 - 2015	M.Sc. in Astronomy at the University of Oslo, thesis titled "Cosmolo-
	gical Simulations with Disformally Coupled Symmetron Fields".
2010 - 2013	B.Sc. in Physics, Astronomy and Meteorology" at the University of

Professional experience

2015 - 2019PhD student, University of Oslo. Developed and extended several pieces of high-performance parallel software for studying alternative theories of gravity. Collaborated in a highly international research field. 25 % teaching duty in bachelor level astronomy course, including development of software for the students. 2012 - 2015Four semesters as group teacher (Teaching Assistant) in different courses at UiO and HiO (now OsloMet). Subjects include mathematics, physics and informatics. I answered questions about programming and science concepts, as well as graded exams. 2013 - 201426.7 % position as mathematics teacher with responsibility for a class of VG1 mathematics students. Blackboard and powerpoint lectures, and helping students with exercises. Designing and grading tests. Final grading of students. 2019 -Consultant, Expert Analytics

Languages

English Fluent
French Basic
Norwegian Native
Polish Intermediate

Personal skills

Analytical and Good ability to understand and break down a new problem in a logical creative way, and to provide creative solutions when needed. Communication Many years of experience in teaching science and programming. Good and teaching ability to understand and explain difficult concepts. Intuitive and Not afraid to explore unknown problems and technology. Ability to curious delve into and learn new material quickly. Able to implement a physical model into computer code in an efficient Modeling and data analysis way, while avoiding numerical problems. Developing custom tools to analyse the output and compare it with measurements.

Some interests and hobbies

Music Digital music editing, as well as several analog instruments including:

drums, guitar, sitar, piano and gong

Personal Personal development, learning and experiencing new things, traveling,

puzzles, cooking

Sports and Weightlifting, yoga, hiking, skiing, golf

nature

Test More stuff

expertanalytics.no

Extended descriptions of selected projects

Activity Cosmological simulations with scalar fields

Period 2013 – 2019 Role Researcher Staffing Team of 3

Description Together with my supervisors (David Mota and Claudio Llinares), I

extended the freely available cosmological N-body code RAMSES to simulate an additional disformal scalar degree of freedom. This introduces a highly non-linear hyperbolic differential equation for the scalar field, as well as complex equations for the extra forces on the N-body particles. RAMSES is written in FORTRAN, and is designed to run in parallel on supercomputing clusters. Hence, I paid special attention to memory usage, efficient MPI parallelism, and low level code optimization. The output data ranged from gigabytes to terabytes, and statistical analysis of the output was necessary to draw scientific conclusions. I wrote several auxillary tools for data and image analysis, as well as a 1-dimensional hyperbolic solver in spherical symmetry for more detailed study of the non-linear equation of motion of the scalar

field.

Tools Physical modeling, statistical data analysis, image analysis, scientific

writing, FORTRAN, Python

Activity Development and use of student software AST2000 Mission Control

Period 2015 – 2017

Role Developer and tester

Staffing Team of 8

Description As part of my work as a group teacher in AST1100/AST2000, I had

a leading role as developer of the Python backend that the students used for visualisation. The code procedurally generates a virtual solar system for each student, and during the course the student interacts with this code to launch a satellite from one planet, achieve orbit around another planet and land a landing module safely. After finishing development and writing the exercises and user manual, I had the main responsibility for updating the codebase when students reported bugs

and inconsistencies.

Tools Analytical modeling, procedural generation, user interfacing, pedago-

gical writing, Python, LaTeX